Finding Aid for the Allyn Joslyn Papers PASC.0293
UCLA Library Special Collections
Allyn Joslyn papers
circa 1920s-1970s
UCLA Library Special Collections
Joslyn, Allyn
PASC.0293
9.9 Linear Feet (19 boxes and 3 flat boxes)
Versatile character actor Allyn Joslyn's acting career spanned from the 1920's to the 1970's. The collection documents Joslyn's professional accomplishments as an actor and entertainer, and includes scripts for motion pictures, television, radio, and stage; press clippings focused on Joslyn's career; photographs (mainly stills) from various film, television, and stage productions; and a small amount of correspondence and ephemera.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Audio materials in this collection are restricted and require advance notice for use.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9956029443606533
Biography
Allyn Morgan Joslyn was born in Milford, PA. There is conflicting information about the date of his birth; it has been reported as July 21, 1901 and July 21, 1905. As a teenager, he began his career on the live stage and acted in many plays throughout the 1920s and '30s. In 1935, he starred on Broadway in George Abbott's production of Boy Meets Girl. His role as Robert Law brought accolades and led him to Hollywood.
Joslyn made his motion picture debut in They Won't Forget (1937). (The film also marked the first film appearance of Lana Turner.) Over the next several decades, Joslyn acted in numerous motion pictures for all of the major studios, often in comedic roles. Notable motion pictures in which Joslyn appeared include Only Angels Have Wings (1939), My Sister Eileen (1942), Heaven Can Wait (1943), and Titanic (1953), among others. Joslyn played the role of Mortimer Brewster in the original Broadway production of Arsenic and Old Lace (1941); however, the role was played by Cary Grant in the film version (1944). While working in both theater and motion pictures, he was actively writing and acting in radio shows.
Joslyn's television career included lead roles in the series, The Eve Arden Show, where he had an ongoing role as George Howell (1957-58), and McKeever and the Colonel where Joslyn starred as Colonel Harvey Blackwell (1962-63). He was a regular on The Ray Bolger Show (1953-54) and also made many guest appearances in a variety of television productions throughout the 1950s and '60s. These include The Addams Family, Rawhide, The Untouchables, and several programs for Ford Theatre. Joslyn made his final film appearance in The Brothers O'Toole (1973). He died of cardiac failure on January 21, 1981 at the Motion Picture and Television Country House in Woodland Hills, CA.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of scripts, press clippings, photographs, correspondence, and memorabilia documenting the career of actor and entertainer Allyn Joslyn. The bulk of the collection is comprised of scripts for motion picture, television, radio and stage projects featuring/including Joslyn and/or items which may have been submitted to Joslyn for his consideration. Included are scripts for My Sister Eileen (1942), Heaven Can Wait (1943), The Eve Arden Show (1957-58), and McKeever and the Colonel (1962-63), among others. There is also a small collection of stills from selected motion picture, stage and television productions, including Boy Meets Girl, No Time for Comedy, and McKeever and the Colonel, among others.
The press clippings include a mixture of reviews, publicity, and promotional write-ups about Joslyn and/or the various projects or events in which he was involved during his career. There is also a small amount of correspondence that includes letters, telegrams, and/or cards related to both personal matters and professional activities. The memorabilia is from events or performances that Joslyn was either involved with or attended. Additionally, there is a small number of entertainment-related magazine publications that do not appear related to Joslyn's personal or professional life.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Motion Picture Projects
Radio Projects
Stage Productions
Television Projects
Correspondence
Memorabilia
Publicity Stills and Photographs
Press Reviews and Publicity
Publications
Clippings.; Television scripts.; Film scripts.; Actors -- United States -- Archives; Film stills.; Joslyn, Allyn, -1981--Archives.
- Motion Picture Projects, (ca.1930s-ca. 1972s, bulk 1938-1958); Boxes 2, 5-11, 18-19
  Scope and Contents note
  The Motion Picture series contains script material and a small collection of stills related to motion picture projects featuring or including Joslyn. Included are scripts for My Sister Eileen, This Thing Called Love, Titanic, and Heaven Can Wait, among others. Additionally, there are scripts which may have been submitted to Joslyn for his consideration. The stills document selected film projects in which Joslyn was involved such as Café Society, Deep South, Hollywood Hotel, and No Time for Comedy, among others. The series is arranged alphabetically by motion picture project title. See also the Press Clipping series.
  - unspecified
    - Bedtime Story (A) - magazine ad tear out, no date (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Bell for Adano (A) - final script, 1944 Oct 27 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Beyond Tomorrow - loose script page, no date (Box 11, Folder 7)
      General note
      Appears to be Beyond Tomorrow.
    - Birthday - final script, 1942 Dec 14 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Thought to be released as Heaven Can Wait.
    - Brothers O'Toole (The) (1 of 2) - final script and revised pages, 1972-73 (Box 18, Folder 10)
      With call sheets, photocopies letters from colleagues, studio newsletter, and press clippings. Caricature drawing of Joslyn moved to Box 19, Folder 3.
    - Brothers O'Toole (The) (2 of 2) - caricature of Joslyn, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Signed by Mike. Removed from Box 18, Folder 10.
    - Café Society - 9 photographs, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Café Society (1 of 2) - script pages and revised buff script, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Café Society (2 of 2) - first white script and script pages, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Christmas in Connecticut - script, 1944 Mar 20 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Clementine - final script, 1947 Mar 18 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Thought to be released as Mickey.
    - Colonel Effingham's Raid - revised final script, 1944 Nov-Dec (Box 6, Folder 3)
      With revised pages dated Dec 1944.
    - Dark Waters - first draft script with changes, 1944 Mar (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Deep South - 47 photographs., no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Thought to be released as They Won't Forget.
    - Expensive Husbands - 13 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Faculty Row - script, 1942 Nov (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Thought to be released as Young Ideas.
    - Fast and Furious - loose script pages, 1939 Aug (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Fast and Furious - script, 1939 Jul 28 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Fastest Gun Alive (The) - script and souvenir program, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Girl Trouble - first draft continuity script, 1942 Mar 31 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Harriet Craig - fourth revised final draft loose script pages, 1950 Apr (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Heaven Can Wait - ad from Hollywood Reporter, 1943 July (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Hit the Deck - script, 1954 Jun (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Hollywood Hotel - 34 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Home Sweet Homicide - first draft continuity script, 1946 Jan 10 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Horn Blows at Midnight (The) - part one revised final script pages, 1943- 1944 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      With added scenes and retakes dated Oct 1944.
    - Hot Spot - final script and playbill, 1941 Jul 11 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Thought to be released as I Wake Up Screaming.
    - I Love Melvin - script, 1952 Apr (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - If I Had My Way - 13 photographs, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      One item inscribed by Allyn Joslyn.
    - If I Had My Way - revised final script, 1940 Feb 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - If the Shroud Fits - first draft, 1943 Jan 26 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Thought to be released as Dangerous Blondes.
    - If You Knew Susie - 3 photographs, ca. 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Imitation of Life - revised final screenplay, 1958 Jul 10 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Immortal Sergeant - 5 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Thought to be from Immortal Sergeant based on press clippings from collection.
    - Immortal Sergeant - revised final script, 1942 Aug (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Imposter (The) - script, 1943 Aug (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Innocent Affair - script, ca. 1948 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Island in the Sky - revised script, 1953 Jan (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Jazz Singer (The) - part one revised final script, 1952 Jul (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Junior Miss - final script, 1945 Jan 20 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Lady in Ermine (The) - first draft continuity script, 1947 Jun 3 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Lady of the House (The) - fourth revised final draft, 1950 Mar (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Thought to be released as Harriet Craig.
    - Marriage of Inconvenience - script, no date (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Miracle of the Moor - script, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - My Sister Eileen - revised final draft script, 1942 May 19 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Nearer My God to Thee - revised final script, 1952 Oct 22 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Thought to be released as Titanic.
    - Nightmare in the Sun - final revised script, 1963 Jul 31 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - No Time for Comedy - 59 photographs, ca. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - No Time for Comedy - final script, 1940 Apr 4 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Octopus and Miss Smith (The) - part one final script, 1949 Feb 10 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Thought to be released as The Lady Takes a Sailor.
    - Once Upon a Thursday - script, 1942 Feb (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Thought to be released as The Affairs of Martha.
    - Only Angels Have Wings - 2 mounted photographs, no date (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Thought to be a behind the scenes shot. Title thought to be formerly known as Plane No. 4. See also Box 1, Folder 14 for additional stills.
    - Only Angels Have Wings - loose script pages, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Thought to be Only Angels Have Wings based on pages labeled: Plane Number Four and character names.
    - Personal History - test scenes, no date (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Released as Foreign Correspondent.
    - Plane No. 4 - 10 photographs., no date (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Thought to be released as Only Angels Have Wings. See also Box 19, Folder 4 with photographs for Only Angels Have Wings.
    - Public Pigeon No. 1 - first draft estimating script, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Rendezvous in Rio - final draft script, 1946 Apr (Box 9, Folder 9)
      With revised pages dated May 3, 1946.
    - Repeat Performance - script, 1946 Aug 7 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Rich Man, Poor Man - incomplete revised estimating script, 1946 Sep 20 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Shining Hour (The) - 1 photograph, no date (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Shining Hour (The) - incomplete script, 1938 Aug 18 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Shocking Miss Pilgrim (The) - 5 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Shocking Miss Pilgrim (The) - shooting final script, 1945 Nov (Box 10, Folder 3)
      With revisions dated Nov 10, 1945 and music for The Back Bay Polka. Radio sound recording in Box 21 Folder ?.
    - Shocking Miss Pilgrim (The) - shooting final script, 1945 Nov (Box 10, Folder 4)
      With revisions dated Nov 10 and Nov 19, 1945. See also sound recording, Box 21 Folder ?.
    - So This is New York - first draft screenplay, ca. 1947 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Spring Parade - revised final script, 1940 May 18 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Stalk the Hunter - final draft script, 1944 May 8 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Thought to be released as Strange Affair.
    - Sweethearts - 2 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Sweethearts - script and loose script pages, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - This Thing Called Love - loose script pages, no date (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Appears to be This Thing Called Love.
    - This Thing Called Love - revised final draft script, 1940 Aug 24 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - This Thing Called Love - revised pages for second revised final draft script, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      With shooting schedules and retakes pages.
    - This Thing Called Love - second revised final draft script, 1940 Sep 11 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Titanic - 1 photograph, no date (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Very Remarkable Fellow (A) - final script, 1946 Aug 28 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Wife Takes a Flyer - ad from Variety (3 copies), 1942 May (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Will You Love Me in December? - final script, 1950 Oct 27 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Thought to be released as As Young As You Feel.
    - You Gotta Stay Happy - script, 1948 Apr (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Radio Projects, (1935, 1940s); Boxes 15, 21
  The Radio series contains script material and a small number of audio recordings for radio projects in which Joslyn was involved. The series is arranged alphabetically into sub-series by radio series title. The processor created the sub-series Unknown Radio Projects for items not identified with a produced radio program and which may have been project ideas submitted to Joslyn for his consideration. The files within each sub-series are arranged alphabetically by episode or program title. Among the scripts are writings for The Joan Davis Show and advertising spots for Velure Lotion. The sound recordings include My Life of Caroline, Skylark, and Talk of the Town presented by the Lady Esther Screen Guild Players. (The "Screen Guild was a charity show donating all star fees" to the Motion Picture Relief Fund which was used to build the Motion Picture Country House for "aging and indigent screen stars." Joslyn would later live his last days at the Motion Picture Country House). Use of audio material requires production of listening copies. See also Press Clippings series for press clippings.
  - Hollywood Star Time
    - Junior Miss - audio recordings, 1946 Mar 24 (Box 21)
      RESTRICTED ACCESS - Use of audio material requires production of listening copies. Prepared for Joslyn by Foote, Cone, and Belding. Includes additional Hollywood Star Time recording dated 7/28/44. (4 discs). Personalized record album in box 22.
    - Junior Miss - personalized record album, 1946 Mar 24 (Box 22)
      Discs in box 21.
  - Joan Davis Show
    - Joan Davis Show - script, 1947 Feb 24 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Lady Esther Screen Guild Players
    - My Life With Caroline - audio recordings, 1945 Oct 8 (Box 21)
      RESTRICTED ACCESS - Use of audio material requires production of listening copies. Prepared for Joslyn compliments of the Lady Esther company. (3 discs). Personalized record album in box 22.
    - My Life with Caroline - personalized record album, 1945 Oct 8 (Box 22)
    - Skylark - audio recordings, 1943 Aug 23 (Box 21)
      RESTRICTED ACCESS - Use of audio material requires production of listening copies. Prepared for Joslyn compliments of the Lady Esther company. Includes additional unlabeled disc. (4 discs). Personalized record album in box 22.
    - Skylark - personalized record album, 1943 Aug 23 (Box 22)
    - Talk of the Town (The) - audio recordings, 1946 May 13 (Box 21)
      RESTRICTED ACCESS - Use of audio material requires production of listening copies. Prepared for Joslyn compliments of the Lady Esther company. Includes additional disc labeled The Shocking Miss Pilgrim. (4 discs). Personalized record album in box 22.
    - Talk of the Town (The) - personalized record album, 1946 May 13 (Box 22)
  - This Is My Best
    - Employment agreement signed by JAJ, 1945 Oct 17 (Box 15, Folder 18)
      From Batten, Barton, Durstine and Osborn - for Cresta Blanca Wine Company and thought to be for the episode: Venus Didn't Diet.
  - Unknown Radio Projects
    - Julie's Mr. Ames - tentative outline, no date (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Red Mallory - proposal and script pages, no date (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Velure Lotion - advertising spot scripts, 1935 Sep (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Voice of Broadway - script, 1942 Jun 9 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      Dorothy Kilgallen, Voice of Broadway, sponsored by Johnson and Johnson.
- Stage Projects, (1924, late 1930s, early 1940s, and early 1950s); Boxes 2, 3-5
  The Stage Projects consists of scripts for stage productions featuring Joslyn and/or submitted to him for his consideration. The series is arranged alphabetically by production title. Several of the scripts are undated; dated materials range from 1937-1952. See also the Press Clippings series.
  - unspecified
    - Adam's Other Wife - play script, no date (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Also known as Mrs. Curtis the First.
    - Afternoon - A Play in Three Acts by Dorcas Ruthenburg, no date (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - All That Glitters - 9 photographs, ca. 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Thought to be for stage production.
    - And the Angels Sang by Bella and Samuel Spewack - play script., no date (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Arsenic and Old Lace - 7 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Arsenic and Old Lace - promotional ephemera, no date, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Astrologer Fainted (The) - play script, no date (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Boy Meets Girl - - 36 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Thought to be for stage production. Some items identified as Boy Meets Girl by Bella and Samuel Spewack A George Abbott Production Cort Theatre, N.Y. and/or Photograph by Vandamm Studio, N.Y.
    - Boy Meets Girl - playbills, no date (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Cloud Chamber (The) - A Comedy in Three Acts by Robert L. Craig - play script, 1942 Aug (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Collector's Item - Actors' Equity Association agreement form signed by AJ, 1952 Jan 11 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Collector's Item - annotated play script and playbills, no date (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Script is untitled and thought to be Collector's Item based on character names and story line. Playbills from Booth Theatre.
    - Debt (The) - play script, no date (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Also known as Palace on the Sand.
    - Desert Isle - script pages, no date (Box 15, Folder 14)
      Thought to be stage production.
    - Don't Run, Walk - Some Comedy, Farce, Mystery and What Not in Three Acts - play script, 1939 Mar 17 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Drat! The Cat! - play script, no date (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Fancy Meeting You Again - play script, no date (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Flahooley - play script, no date (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Hand in Glove - play script, 1943 Jan 27 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Happy Ending (The) - play script, no date (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - He Drew a Blank - play script, no date (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Highland Fling (A) - play script, no date (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Honesty is the Pest Policy - A Three Act Play - title page only, no date (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - It's Always Fair Weather!! - play script, no date (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Magnum Opus - play script, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Misalliance - playbills (3 copies), no date (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Directed by Joslyn.
    - Once There Was a Russian - play script, no date (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Overtons (The) - play script, no date (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Paolo and Francesca - 6 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Police! Police! - play script, no date (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Prodigal Father (The) - play script, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Promise Past the Night - play script, no date (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Ready-Made Tomorrows - play script, no date (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Rx - One Pill in Hot Water - play script, no date (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Silk Hat Harry - play script, no date (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Six Characters in Search of an Author - 1 photograph, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - This is on Me - play script, no date (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Tobacco Road - playbill, no date (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Project of Dorothy Yockel (AJ's wife).
    - Together Again - play script, no date (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Untitled play script, no date (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Television Projects, (1950s-mid 1960s); Boxes 11-15, 18
  The Television Projects series consists mostly of scripts and a small number of stills and press clippings for television projects where Joslyn was either a featured player or had a guest role. The series is arranged alphabetically into subseries by television series or television program title. The processor created the sub-series Other Television Projects for the small number of items not identified with a produced television program and which may have been project ideas submitted to Joslyn for his consideration. The files within each sub-series are arranged alphabetically by episode or project title. Among the many television projects are 25-plus scripts and a small number of stills from the 1960s television series McKeever and the Colonel, where Joslyn starred as Colonel Harvey Blackwell from 1962-1963. Additionally, there is a small number of scripts, stills, and press clippings for The Eve Arden Show, where Joslyn had an ongoing role as George Howell (1957-58). See also the Press Clipping series.
  - 20th Century-Fox Hour (The)
    - Christopher Bean - revised final script, 1955 Oct 17 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Addams Family
    - Gomez the Politician - revised script pages, 1964 Sep (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Alaskans (The)
    - Trail North - revised final script, 1959 Apr 27 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Alfred Hitchcock Presents
    - Make Me An Offer - script, 1959 Jan 13 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Right Price (The) - script pages, no date (Box 11, Folder 15)
      Thought to be for Alfred Hitchcock Presents series.
  - Bachelor Father
    - Bentley and the Travel Agent - script, 1960 Feb 17 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Ben Casey
    - When Givers Prove Unkind - final draft script, 1965 Jul 23 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Cheyenne
    - Top Hand - revised final script, 1957 Sep 27 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Chrysler Theatre
    - The Square Peg - revised script, 1964 Jan (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Eve Arden Show (The)
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - 2 photographs, no date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - magazine publications, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 18)
      Reference or mention of the Eve Arden Show: TV-Radio Life, TV Radio Mirror, and TV Star Parade.
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - press clippings, 1958 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - press clippings, 1957-58 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - press clippings, 1957? Sep-Dec (Box 18, Folder 17)
      TV Guide review and TV Guides (5) listing the Eve Arden Show.
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - press clippings (1 of 3), 1957 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - press clippings (2 of 3), 1957 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - press clippings (3 of 3), 1957 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Eve Arden Show (The) - printed ephemera, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      Congratulatory telegram, tickets, and press release for Temple Foundation in Philadelphia.
    - Hollywood Offer (The) -revised script, 1957 Dec 6 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Liza and the Harvard Man -first draft script, 1958 Jan 22 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Liza Meets Young Korea - first draft script, 1957 Dec 30 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Liza's Nightmare - script, no date (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Liza's Reunion Dance - first draft script, 1957 Nov 18 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Mary's Report Card - first draft script, 1957 Nov 27 (Box 12, Folder 10)